all right hello everyone
it's august 12 2022
and we are in
guest stream number 26.1
from users to sensemakers on the pivotal
role of stigma social annotation in the
quest for collective sense making
this should be a great presentation and
discussion and so i'll pass it to ronin
to introduce the context and take it
away with the presentation so thanks
everyone for joining and ronan and will
thanks for coming on
awesome yeah thanks daniel for for
putting this on and uh yeah excited to
be here and have this uh discussion
i think it's our first time discussing
this paper like long form so looking
forward to it
um but yeah this paper actually code
yeah for some context
this presentation will be related to the
paper
that we wrote together as a group um
and yeah it was also represented in the
conference on hypertext and social media
in june
of this year in barcelona uh so today
we'll go over kind of the key points of
the paper and
uh try to dive into more details uh kind
of explore directions that we didn't
have time to address with this sort of
short kind of presentation of the paper
of the conference um and then we'll
later sort of open a wider discussion uh
talk about how this
is sort of
informing the work of our
collective and discussion of some
initial projects that we're
working on in the context of this of
this research including active inference
and some other
projects like vo and a few more so yeah
looking forward to a lot to talk about
so yeah probably we should start with
the definitions or some of the terms
we're going to be using in
this because we introduced a lot of a
lot of words that can mean a lot of
things to a lot of people so
i think
yeah sense making is something that has
a lot of different missions the one
worst of working working definition
we're looking at processes by which
individuals and groups make sense of
their environment by organizing and send
data to the environment is understood
well enough to enable reasonable
decisions so we do science making all
the time in physical environments and
online environments as we'll see
so there's this kind of incoming stream
of sense data
coming from the environment and
we have to sort of uh adapt and
handle this this kind of stream of data
to inform our decisions uh incorporate
it into our decision making process
um
but yeah so
scent making is is a kind of broad
subject in terms of like where where
collectively
descent making some kind of
uh
[Music]
a kind of typical sort of uh thing you
might hear from you know media you'll
hear things like like this what we
brought here so yeah the quality of our
democratic life depends the public
having the fact that being able to make
sense of them
uh and there's this feeling that this
isn't really happening anymore so
that's why a lot of people are worried
about the future of democracy
this is just kind of an interesting uh
research here on the right that's
showing
how polarized and how like how much we
don't have a shared sense uh
what's going
so you can look at things like
uh you know the topics people are
looking at and seeing on
cnn or fox news uh and see like how
different the coverage is of each of
those uh networks for for the same topic
so yeah so things like trump's failures
will get a lot of
uh a lot of uh
being addressed like very heavily in cnn
but uh
not seeing much on fox and then vice
versa
democrats
so yeah people are living in a really
different world because of our
information environments so this is kind
of a motivating background for why we're
why are we getting interested in this
because really our democracies are at
stake as a lot of people have already
noticed
and yeah just kind of another word of
sort of disclaiming
that
stem making is a wicked problem um
and
yeah we definitely aren't going to claim
to have like the solution to making our
collective sense making
it will require many different solutions
and it's kind of an ongoing problem so
we'll kind of make progress on it and
then we'll have new problems
progress
it's very interdisciplinary so there's a
lot of stakeholders of different sort of
schools of thought that and practice
that will need to be involved
so we're looking at kind of we're trying
to look at one angle
and
that is how platforms shape our
information landscapes
online
and and we kind of
noticed two things two uh sort of
important
things about platforms that make them
what we call it perilous
so for one there's a notion of
centralization where a few giant
platforms
facebook people youtube
etc have gained unprecedented control
over attention by controlling the needs
to create search and distributed
information
and two
opacities where
platforms network data and algorithms
are hidden away from the public
so there's like
all the sort of oversight that could
help us
you know issues with our information
landscape or
really not we don't really have
uh we don't really have any way to to
handle this currently because of this
opacity
um
yeah
the kind of dual scrolling has become
the
icon of our times and we don't know
what's
behind
our screens like why isn't something
being shown to us we kind of have to
at times you know vague or like the
different
motivations for why that might be but
yeah we really are kind of
yeah they're controlling your screens
and we're on those screens for most of
the day so
definitely a lot of power over what
we're our information types
yeah
so
you know it's clear how we got here
right it's kind of convenient you know
we have these platforms that we have tik
tok and twitter they offer us they do
offer us like very
high quality in some regards like they
give us information that we're
interested in we like seeing you know
what we're looking at on instagram like
seeing the videos we're watching on
kickback they give us like this
short-term dopamine kick but of course
uh
then when we look into the
global picture
we can
start seeing the cost of this the
platforms are involved in a host of
deeply problematic social phenomena like
polarization information epistemic
extraction
and yeah it's interesting to sort of go
into the literature scientific
literature on this because uh you know
scientists yeah this is just just one uh
uh tweet that i am very particular you
know the most important paper of my
career talking about
this kind of
uh
dramatic restructuring of the human
communication
not by these platforms with no aim other
than selling ads uh yeah the paper is
called stewardship of global collective
behavior it's a very inspiring call to
action
this is a crisis businessman just like
ecology and sustainability or crisis
disciplines we need to understand how
we're going to help save the planet from
ruining nature so we have a similar kind
of crisis that's what they're sort of
claiming
on the front of uh
yeah on the front of like the
information online online environments
uh that people are looking at
so
yeah so there's a lot of work on this so
this is you know the scientific side
this
book is another kind of interesting
uh very inspiring book uh that also kind
of puts the fingers squarely on this
kind of challenging attention economy
you know that says
that if we're going to surround the
minimal challenges we face today
uh we'll need to be giving the right
field of attention right things
the book is called stand out over light
talks about freedom and resistance for
the attention
and these are all very inspiring sort of
uh works and
the question is
where do we go from here so we're really
inspired and we understand that the
information environments are very sort
of putting us in this parallel
what can we do so
this is also from the same book uh we're
kind of working toward
where we can start to actually be doing
work on helping rethink these
information so
our quest kind of begins and with this
kind of realization and again this is
from the
book we presented earlier if we're at
all serious about promoting freedom and
autonomy in the digital age what that
would entail starting to assert and
defend our freedom of attention this is
also a very evocative kind of uh passage
freedom of attention yeah what does that
look like on online spaces there's a lot
of ways you can think about freedom of
attention
uh
yeah so
a lot of this work is is sort of i think
attempt to sort of articulate one vision
of what freedom of attention looks like
uh online
uh yeah so you know we have this quest
we we we're trying to sort of put this
then more into more time people it's
what it means
as a spoiler you know what we talked
about in this in
in this presentation what we talked
about in the paper uh we look at we take
signature to be some kind of unifying
concept that's underlying attention and
scientific so if we need some place to
start sort of a concrete solid place to
put our feet and start working uh we
think stigma energy is a really useful
concept many of you probably haven't
even heard of stigmatizing i surely
haven't until i met daniel here
i learned about you know collective
intelligence and
insects
so yeah we'll start from ground zero
stigma g is
collective behavioral behavioral
coordination among entities via
perception and modification of shared
environment and this i think really did
originated in studies
of uh coordination in ants
so you know the classic sort of example
is trail pheromones and sleeves and
we'll go into more detail on that
so you know an ant leaves some kind of
environment modification in the form of
a trail pheromone and then it's
attracted to it and there's some this
collective intelligent behavior emerging
as a result
another important thing to say about
sigmar g is is
this on the next slide yeah so
it's really kind of profound when you
go into it because you know we shape the
environment and it shapes us in a very
profound way um
some even go as far to say that
environments act as a distributed memory
system for a collective organism
so if any of you are familiar with the
extended mind hypothesis in cognitive
science how our tools are sort of
extensions of our cognition so stigmaty
is a sort of extended mind for
collectives
um
and then we have these diverging
feedback loops where you can go back
here you know we have agents and they're
producing some kind of
mark that's where stigma in greek you
know mark
is coming from so agents are producing
these results of action and that's
stimulating you know the same agent or
other agent and uh so there's a kind of
coupling between the environment the
agent acting on the environment
stimulating other agents for action
uh and then this kind of emerging global
sense
uh
yeah also important
no large scale coordination is possible
without the energy so if you go like
above n equals 25
then
then you need emerging communication
it's not like you know we can do zoom
calls with a thousand people right we
need other methods of coordination
synergies there's this like main method
of doing it and internet modifying
environments that other people are
participating in we'll go through a lot
of examples but the point is that we
really need to create healthy stigmargic
infrastructure
for a large scale coordination
and then
yeah we can ask is stigmatic
infrastructure
that is provided to us today in online
environments how healthy is it uh so
we'll talk about that in a minute
um
yeah if you have anything you wanted to
say about uh like
other aspects of synergy that we
may or may not be touching here
maybe later on the uh types of stigma
yes
cool yeah so that's our next slide
yeah um
yeah we took a lot of integration from
this work
uh i'm leslie marsh on
uh stigmatic epistemology and
and they give this kind of useful
distinction between
two kinds of stigma g and you have
content creating stigma g
they call it semitectonic i think that's
they're drawn from some other uh
literature i think
um
oh cool yeah acts as a sign of book
because i wasn't sure that actually
nice so yeah content creating energy
versus signaling signature which is
marker based so the examples are helpful
here to understand what h mean in a
physical environment uh content creating
is like actually carving out a trail
which other agents are going to see and
you know use that uh they take out a
different kind of sign and you should go
over this trail and not just like
randomly off into the woods
um
and in a digital environment you might
think of things like writing a document
so you're actually modifying the digital
environment by writing words so that's
kind of the content creating sigmarching
and on the other side you have signaling
stigma gene the marker base where
looking at things like pheromone trails
and physical environments so ads aren't
actually modifying the environment in
any sort of meaningful way i mean
they're just doing it as sort of
communication experience they're not
changing the environment by like moving
some debris out of the path or creating
a path just like marking some kind of uh
trail for other ants
in the digital environment you can think
of a sort of
uh
highlighting or tagging is you know the
counterpart to that in the physical
environment so we'll definitely go into
this also in detail
now
we are focusing here on this big
building based stigma g we kind of
highlight that this is what we want to
focus on um
because actually
yeah this doesn't get as much attention
thinking about online environments as
we'll see
a lot of people are talking about this
kind of
content creating stigma g and sort of
people don't mention it
but people talk about how we create
content how we share it online uh not as
many people are talking about it's kind
of how we're sharing markers online so
this is why we decided uh this is kind
of an important focus not going to bring
to attention
yeah and did you want to say anything
else about texas
yeah
in the physical case
the left side the
actions that modify the niche
and clear out the trail or move pebbles
and do the nest architecture and so on
the analogy to content creation is very
clear like there's some arrangement of
mass
that isn't where it was previously and
then on the right side where in the
physical case it's more like the
pheromone trails which are transient or
longer lasting accumulations
and uh
as i hope we can
draw out on the next slide and going
forward
there is this kind of accumulation
across both types like somebody might
make an initial
post on a social media
but then somebody else might annotate it
and
it blurs the line between what is a
reaction what's a pheromone and what is
like building another piece of content
like if somebody responds with a image
is that like building or is that like
annotating and marking and i think that
points to the need to have a a design
language and a way of framing this
question that is able to encompass like
the pure classical content delivery like
a paper publication
and pure classical
transient marking on some digital
context and everything in between so
that we don't have to categorize
different communication acts along the
lines that they've been defined by
essentially the platforms that got us
into this position
yeah yeah yeah no that's that's that's
really great and i think here this maybe
creates a misleading impression there's
some kind of uh pattern categorization
it's like taxonomy but yeah there's
really a spectrum between
marker base and content creating uh so
it's kind of a yeah it's there's all the
grayers in between and some things some
markers are almost content in their own
right
yeah if i add a highlight with some
words on it is that really content
creating or is that annotation or like
signaling so yeah definitely a lot of
a lot of spectrum here and this is just
to say that we're focused more on this
side of the spectrum and then really we
can talk about this spectrum uh give a
better idea of what we're looking at
so we're looking at the merging markers
on the web um and the reason we're
focused on them is because in a lot of
respects they function as sort of the
digital traces of human attention um and
you're looking at things like reactions
um
associations that people might make you
know hyperlinks like oh i think this
content relates to smaller content we do
it all the time
in our tools like notion you're you know
you're linking to some other page you
think this reminds me
yeah tags some tagging content saying oh
this is the on the topic of i don't know
this decentralized distance or something
like that
uh and click through data is interesting
this is an implicitly yeah an explicit
and implicit marker so some of these
markers people are kind of doing this
they're
you know leaving consciously the digital
pheromone trail
by liking some posts and other times
it's actually like you can think of it
as an implicit marker where it's just
like the trail that we're traveling on
the web uh we're leaving this marker and
it is definitely being harvested right
like click through data is very valuable
as we can we'll see also later the
platforms
are selling and importing um
but yeah there's the difference in like
what people people might not think
they're even creating any kind of data
here people today are more sort of aware
of it but uh
yeah i think there's a lot of
interesting these are some interesting
future directions
if we're talking about like
implicit versus explicit so
there might be things that are more
implicit you know
in the future for example pupil
measurements or gaze tracking brain
computer interfaces
so this is just you know where you're
looking on a screen could also be a
magic
marker given that someone is recording
it you know it's getting recorded in
some kind of medium
and being used to sort of guide someone
else's attention yes then that is a
stigmatic marker if no one is recording
it then it's you could say yeah it's not
actually a suggestion
there are definitely yeah there's a few
things to say about this one is that the
reason these markers are so important is
because they're very cheap to create
but they have a very high information
content so this is why you know machine
learning
um research researchers and
practitioners will pay a lot of money
for human annotated data annotations
like very
it can be you know a few bits of
information what label is some category
uh but it's very high information
content because the human looked at this
picture and decided okay this is a dog
so these things are very high
information content and that makes them
very valuable
and they're also cheap to create and
interpret so yeah this makes markers
very uh valuable
but it also creates kind of challenges
with uh
ethics
user consent
uh how the data is being used privacy
because
this thing is very valuable but on the
other hand we're also creating a lot of
it without even thinking so
should this be ours
uh or should they help you guys
so a lot of questions there
cool so
we're getting closer now to certain
understanding where our questions going
so yeah the emerging workers could be
harnessed for healthy collective sense
making but centralized platforms are
regarding them you know now we kind of
can see that
if we look now everywhere we look at
what platforms are doing we can see that
they're actually these dragons that are
hoarding worship workers like everything
we're doing is getting really recorded
uh
without us having much access to it so
the click-through data
likes all this kind of stuff is is very
precious and it's getting
collected by these platforms so
okay we kind of
know where we're going now a little
better i want to say one thing this is
just a little
um yeah go into a little bit of
what we mean when we say healthier
collective symptoms like why do why do
we think that symmetric markers could be
harnessed for health or collective
sentiment so let's try to give a little
more uh insight on like what is
healthier unhealthier uh
you know information comments so yeah we
can look at a few examples just like a
toy example of ants i think maybe can be
illustrative this is kind of the mental
model i had in my mind uh as i was
thinking about this paper so
you know if you're looking at healthy
thicker green ants so an ad you know
find some food source um and they start
bringing back the nest they lay the
pheromone trail that line there sorry
for the poor graphics and other ants are
going to see that trail be attracted to
it and follow it
the food sources consumes and meanwhile
the the pheromone trail is decaying
as the food source is consumed
um eventually you know just the case and
then you know it's going to go there
they need to waste the time because
there's no more food there
that's kind of how the healthy sort of
pheromone for pheromone decay the
the ground you know holds it for some
time and then there's you know the sort
of predictable uh operating
characteristics of it now imagine a
different kind of
uh
a different kind of setup where
you know you have a different kind of
ground right like here i'm using
platform just to be suggestive but you
have a platform which is actually like
swallowing pheromone okay so now ants
are trying to lay the pheromone but it's
kind of decay right so this is already
one way in which the stigmargic
infrastructure is not healthy because
uh in a sense like the answer can find a
food because it's just not gonna be able
they're not gonna be able to lay that
parallel there uh to attract other ants
another thing that could happen
is you know if platforms are over
amplifying so if this kind of ground
instead of uh decaying predictably it
was kind of
for some reason reacting and over
amplifying pheromones so even when the
food source was consumed ants would
still be kind of traversing and
wasting their time uh even when there's
no food there
so another thing you know you can kind
of see the
parallels you know in light spaces
uh yeah the third third thing you might
think of is a case where you have kind
of
um
areas where you can't lay uh
uh you know pheromones you can't leave
the feral trail so uh if there's food
it's outside the area where you can
leave pheromone then ants won't be
finding it because
you know just the properties of the
ground so
these are all kinds of ways in which
there's just trying to give you to sort
of
yeah convey the intuition that there are
it's a very
sort of delicately tuned system and
there are many ways it can be out of
tune and which would you know lead to
very disastrous consequences for the
sort of organism the collective
organisms as a whole
yeah yeah well do you want us to think
about that
uh yeah i was just going to observe that
um
looking back on the concept of sort of
information silos that you discussed
with
uh fox news and cnn um maybe one more
aspect of unhealthy sigmoidy is
some of these stigmargic markers or
trails are visible to one group and
invisible to another group so you you
also have um this failure to create a
shared reality um
i wonder if that's another aspect of
unhealthy big energy yeah definitely i
think that one yeah that would
definitely be another another a great
example where yeah you might have
you know that only a certain part of the
hive is going to be
sensing and then another type that the
other part of the hype is going to be
something they're really going to be
just living in shared
shared uh not shared realities
yeah for sure so i think that's a that's
a great example also
yeah so
yeah those are the few kind of hand
maybe intuitive examples try to get the
uh point across that
if we're looking at healthier
information environments uh they're
going to be highly complex because if
you consider a lot of parameters here
you know just imagine what what's going
on
this is ants so it's relatively simple
and even that when it was complex but um
you have all these different kinds of
markers people are leaving and the
different parameters to reach the
markers and how they're getting spread
and
used to recommend content so a lot of
parameters here
the point is that as designers and
participants in these information
environments uh will need to be able to
assume
more control more decentralized right
because we don't want a central designer
but uh we'll need to be able to play
with these parameters for uh currently
as we discussed there's the opacity and
centralization so very few people
um are able even to make the kind of you
know
to tweak these parameters and they can
do experiments you know like global
scale and they're the only people that
can do them
so yeah that was the point of these
examples so
um
our proposals so finally we can kind of
talk about where where we think uh
fruitful direction would be to go um
yeah we call it open source retention
and we try to draw the parallel to open
source software and decentralization
movement and
the sort of as i was alluding to earlier
they're all about
freeing most of the work
and about creating content creation
sharing
so you have things like github and you
know decentralized currencies like
bitcoin um
all those are examples of you know the
kind of
technology the content creating
stigmatization so we can create code we
can create documents we can you know
publish social media posts
uh all that kind of thing that's content
we're talking about open source tension
we're looking at sort of the complement
of that it's the emerging markers
is anyone looking at this idea of
freeing
the
reactions to count so we're doing a lot
of this kind of work on decentralizing
contemplation but we're actually what
we're kind of the moment is like we're
not actually doing much work on
freeing these kind of reactions to count
so on the technical level we think
that just as we have sort of systems and
platforms
that will help us with protocols that
help us
share our content
we
that's on the technical level like at a
high level and then we have here sort of
just like
the social aspect of the open source
software movement with these kind of
hacker heroes that were building code in
public and uh sharing it without sort of
any
monetary compensation uh then we'll have
a similar kind of
uh we envision kind of a similar kind of
scent maker hero they're sort of the
counterpart and they're and they're
doing kind of curation in public and
they're mindful of their digital
attention traces
so doing kind of open source attention
open source thinking
sort of following these lines of open
source coding
um yeah so
let's look at what open source attention
means for like uh information ecosystems
like how we translate that to the
information ecosystem actually we're
zooming in now we're getting into the
sort of
more in the direction like concrete uh
implementation so
first let's understand like the
platform-centric information because
there's all the new terms we have the
new terminology so
what we can see like okay so these are
the dragons that are hurting our
attention data and how it happens is we
have these kind of
now we can sort of see what's happening
here the the do controlling we're doing
here is kind of a low agency annotation
interface
uh that's collecting our submerging
markers
uh platforms are storing this data
they sell it to advertisers
they use it to drive content discovery
in a way that serves optimizing for
platform groups by serving us new
content that will keep us on our screens
as well as ads that will keep the
advertisers happy
so they can sort of this is the feedback
right they have this they they have the
the control
closed on us because they have the data
and they have the algorithms
now
how might you like do something
alternative that doesn't involve those
uh
dragon platforms uh so what we propose
is a decentralized maker centric
ecosystem so instead of users we have
makers and makers are these kind of
uh
high agency annotators so we can think
of all these personal knowledge
management tools uh notion and rome and
you know we'll look at
vio hopefully later
[Music]
next all these different kinds of
annotation interfaces people are
building these knowledge management
tools you can actually think of them as
annotation interfaces that are
collecting emerging markers
uh but the crucial sort of point is that
we're talking about a
case where
makers are owning these markers this is
all this is this is you know the point
of sort of stealth sovereign storage uh
cell power and data uh you have things
like solid protocol
that allow people to actually control
and own their own data and we're saying
if we apply this testing markers we
actually get this
separation uh decoupling of the content
discovery algorithms and the
mystic merchant markers then you kind of
break up this platform loop and then
content discovery services will need to
be sort of
uh focused and they'll need to be
aligned with
the
take into account the
sort of human-centered
uh incentives so
makers will be able to share data with
these content discovery services and
there'll be a lot of diverse patent
assembly services but they won't have
control over our data and then that's
kind of a way to break up that vicious
cycle
so you can imagine you know
different kinds of feed algorithms that
you'll have like a competing market free
algorithms or you'll have matchmaking
services uh
ai recommendation all kinds of um
diverse new discovery services and and
you can use
all of them or any of them and you know
kind of it incentivizes open source
yeah open source and more human-centered
environment than what we're looking at
previously
right
one of the main challenges this is
like one of the first challenges that
this kind of
proposal is running into is how to scale
up because
um
you know we have this kind of
network effect where we need to compete
essentially with
facebook and twitter and all these huge
established networks because they have
the data to you know provide the high
quality recommendation and we don't have
anything right now so
the idea here is to bootstrap growth and
personal knowledge management tools for
collective knowledge management this is
an idea that's kind of been floating
around
uh
in a lot of different spaces but yeah
this kind of feeling that user curator
knowledge is really stuck in
single-player tools and
and all the while search engines really
aren't doing as well as they could be
doing
how do we build more collectively
curated knowledge that works
not just like these silos
second grade so
um i think one way to look at it is that
yeah
from going
sort of this is swing depending on the
other direction where
if previously there's data silos in the
platform levels so each platform is like
a data style
using that for harmful sort of
purposes
uh this kind of problem is here what's
currently happening is like each of
these
small
relatively small
knowledge management tools is going to
be a data style and they won't be large
enough to sort of reach
yeah critical map they will be large
enough to provide high quality content
discovery so they have some data but
it's not enough so all of them are
competing versus each other
um either none of them are going to be
able to provide like this kind of
uh high enough quality service and they
won't be able to beat the
platforms the big platforms so
what we kind of
proposed here is is a
protocols not platforms uh approach and
this is something that's very sort of
widely
advocated for web three
so you see protocols for all kinds of
all kinds of sort of interoperable
uh online
objects and what we're talking about
here are protocols for
uh merging primitives so you might
imagine a protocol for light or backlink
or other kinds of things we talked about
earlier
uh and that what this effectively would
enable
is having markers
uh being able to you could share markers
essentially so instead of having these
dialogue markers you can actually pool
them so if i'm collecting my reading
list in notions or also doing it in rome
and someone else is doing it in another
app they could also be shared in a
common format and use
uh
for
driving this kind of discovery
so
that is kind of where we're envisioning
it going we took a lot of inspiration
from this uh
very good
uh essay on
protocol stock platforms highly
recommended
so yeah i think kind of the meme firm
meme version of that is
we have these kind of current situations
where these
small independent platforms are are
going to be eaten by the big fish to doc
and twitter and facebook and all those
and the way for these
independent platforms to
coordinate is through
interoperability using protocols for
stigmatic markers
that's kind of our vision
but yeah there's a lot of work to do to
get there um
so some next steps
we are thinking about are
definitely kind of
going deeper into the weeds and a lot of
questions remaining about social
incentives
uh the tech stack
uh malicious use of these kind of
technologies
uh cultural transitions like how do we
do the transition from users to makers
um
this kind of
work that the first this kind of paper
was more like a blue guy idea paper and
it was more like functioning as a call
to action
um to the sort of challenges
we're saying we need to start building
tech for governing our attention
which is sort of something that we
haven't heard much talked about so we
wanted to sort of bring that uh
emphasize that
in this paper uh yeah we
are really
looking for
all kinds of collaborators so check out
our website and connect with us if any
of us interested um
i think we can
yeah maybe
pause there open for discussion
um
awesome questions
thanks for the presentation ronan so for
those who are watching live feel free to
write a comment in the live chat
otherwise we'll if you have any
reflections or thoughts and then we have
a few more
slides to go through in this next steps
phase and that'll include looking a
little bit more at some platform
affordances
and also
talking about how this connects to
active inference
no immediate thoughts here um plenty to
talk about when we get to the
discussion and the questions
yeah
let's go to uh the
uh promising directions
and talk about that and then we'll go
after that to vo and then active
inference
yeah great um
so yeah some promising directions we
kind of became aware of this is actually
even after
after we wrote the paper
um this is an interesting word from a
few years back
on opportunities and challenges around
public web activity tracking so
essentially getting people to look at
experiments human subjects and
explored the kind of affordances for
allowing people to share browsing
activity traces for example like urls i
visited
and time spent on each webpage
information like that so
they gave people a tool that would allow
them to do that inside the browser and
they checked like small
small groups of people
um different kind of friend groups or
research groups
and they kind of lot of interesting
things i think
uh some of the highlights were that they
found that like while people had privacy
concerns they definitely can and will
tailor their sharing
depending on the concept context and
incentives
um
people felt that this made them a lot
more mindful of their browsing behavior
in a lot of times in a good way
which kind of speaks to the
user-to-maker transition uh if people
are sort of being open so it's just like
you write open source code you kind of
make sure it's like high quality because
we know people are looking at it so they
may lose like attention and browsing
um
and people also could kind of feel how
this would help them better sort of
navigate the information landscape
because they were saying like you can
better assess the legitimacy of some
website by knowing how many people
visited it and who visited
this kind of uh
shared you know public information
um yeah this was this book kind of
caught my eye
uh yeah if you ask me i would rather
a thousand a billion times that
researchers for an academic and
humanistic knowledge purposes are the
ones that can map information stored for
humanity rather than private companies
so this is really speaking kind of
people feeling that sort of human traded
church humans or humans
can be healthier information departments
definitely this work also pointed to
sort of the limitations you know it's
like how do we scale up to something
something larger than just a group of
friends so yeah but definitely this is
like a cool intro in
preliminary study um yeah vo uh we have
also definitely a very interesting kind
of preliminary work that will tell us
more about
yeah thanks ronan um
so
vo is it's a prototype stage software
project
um that was actually originally designed
to be a platform that is a kind of
knowledge garden
um a way for people to visually build
their
network of references and make
connections and trace their paths back
um and it was in a sense a way of
creating trails for people between
uh pieces of content in different
platforms or silos and of course the
problem with that as
uh as ronan has discussed is it itself
is in a cycle and is in a platform so
it's a little bit self-defeating it's in
its original conceptualization um so
right now we're actually in a stage
where we're sort of going back to the
drawing board taking this this new
research
and
this new approach
of building a tool that works on an
interoperable protocol using distributed
data instead of a centralized uh data
store with proprietary
mechanisms of interaction and hopefully
we can take vo and make it a a test case
where we can
practically apply the concept of this
common sense protocol to build out a
piece of software where the data can
then be used in other pieces of software
other front ends other search engines
and so on and
in that way start to actually break free
of this um platforms dominate our
attention paradigm and see kind of what
the possibilities and limitations are
we have a short demo that is kind of the
original concept of vo um so we'll go
through that real quick
i don't think the sound will play but
just full screen the video and just play
it and will describe us um yeah okay i
got it yeah yeah if you want to describe
well you can kind of say what we're
seeing here
all right so this is an example of how
vo might work so
it
takes you through a process
of
discovery you can essentially keep track
of what you're interested in learning um
go through the entire search process
look for sources that seem interesting
or relevant to you
and then as you go you can go through
and annotate different pieces um
take detailed notes take excerpts
etc and then as you have new questions
as there are new uh areas that you would
like to search you can essentially
capture those as you go without breaking
your uh train of thought without
breaking your research process
and then from
there vo automatically builds a visual
map of what you've explored and what you
have yet to explore so that you can
continue to build an ongoing
research
map
and then when you come back to this many
months later you have the entire context
of your whole research process visually
laid out for you everything you looked
for everything you found everything you
were interested in but never got around
to so
you kind of take a lot of the burden of
manually managing your recent process
off of
the researcher and allow the technology
to do what the technology does best
um so
largely the way for you to
take
kind of a walk at your own face through
the information you're interested in or
is valuable to you at the level that you
can understand it
so it allows you to sort of self-select
the best learning path
um without really getting lost in
the
platforms and algorithms and
um
i guess content suggestions or even
curated content or courses that might
not be at the proper level of depth for
where you are at the moment um
so
go ahead
yeah oh did you ask the thing
well
go first run and then i'll add a few
notes
um i just wanted to say
like this this is um
i mean that was one of the things that
sort of i think triggered the whole
collaboration and like
got us started on this on this direction
of research um
like seeing what vo can
like you know just playing a few
intriguing things like one is that many
annotation
tools don't provide
uh this kind of
temporal relation between annotations so
they're just like you're annotating
everything and you don't really know the
structure of like how you got there and
where you went from there and things
like laid out in the trail forum
was really evocative and and sort of
thinking about like how would this look
like we could share this kind of
information and like imagining the sort
of multiplayer video where you might be
standing on a node and then you're like
seeing the trails of other people and
maybe it's like even using ai to sort of
highlight the people that are maybe you
know recommended that you should follow
their trails based on stigma g and crowd
signals and ai or whatever um so like
that was very like a
and
yeah one of the thought there about
yeah that you know just yeah i think
there's another thing i want to say like
social vio and the sort of linking
annotations or like two seemed like
really really intriguing directions to
take this
yeah i also um
[Music]
saw that transition between the first
person knowledge management and the
second person that ronan had brought up
earlier
and it hinges on shared landmarks
and so being able to think of these in a
spatial context which maybe we can
return to with active inference and then
being able to go down to just one's own
path
like just like we'd have a trace on
google maps or something like that but
then see multiple paths together and
have curation approaches there and then
i think it's really uh it's a
fascinating tension with this
functionality
the single or the multiplayer case
it could be done in a centralized
platform web 2 strategy and there's even
arguments for why that would be
streamlined more efficient more secure
all these different aspects
yet
in a different way or at a higher level
there are challenges and failure modes
and so on that would be like
dismantling the function potentially for
example
allowing for a centralized point of
control over those path recommendation
algorithms so as long as the
architecture is bundled
then there are certain failure modes
that this is actually like escalating to
the next level people say oh we used to
have the news feed it was linear
and now we have the branching news feed
and it's so much more fun and engaging
but then it's just representing the next
escalation in attention capture
yeah that's a really good observation
oh yeah go ahead
uh yeah that's that's kind of why we're
we're motivated to pull out of this
platform paradigm um and kind of follow
this uh this new approach it's
fundamentally like
all
all we're trying to do is enhance
people's ability to make sense of the
world and if we make a tool
that undermines it
no matter how
cool or fun it is
we failed
so
um bringing it into a context where this
data
is
you can take the same data and use it in
different apps or you can take data from
different apps and use it in here and
you can kind of break free of certain
mechanisms where the fact that the data
is siloed could be used against the end
user
um
and instead create a paradigm
where
this information
can be
acted on and interpreted in a lot of
different ways where there's room for
innovation and insight and creativity
and competition and disruption where
this model can be
evolved outside of just this app by one
team of developers
and can be integrated into different
ways of interacting with information um
and
by freeing it from that
then then the concept isn't only serving
a business or a group a small group of
people it's serving
everybody who stands to benefit from the
concept being available um so that's
kind of what we're trying to do we don't
want to shoot ourselves in the foot
and in the collective violate our
purpose yeah yeah
yeah yeah i was just thinking i just
thought i was thinking of like
like you were talking about the
different kinds of apps like i mean by
letting this beta be free
it opens up like the space of like you
don't really know how to use i mean you
know it's incredibly valuable you can't
even
envision like how
it could be used in different ways i'm
just thinking of for example you know
like learning learning uh apps i think
there's like a lot of intriguing space
there to explore like you know the trail
that someone is making in the beginning
of their steps and some topic is very
different to the trail that someone was
making like an advanced trail and you
could if you could learn these different
kinds of trails you could build like
really cool
online curriculum
um services that's one thing i was
thinking of but there's just like so
many others uh
and i think there's just a lot of
questions you know people are maybe
thinking themselves like
yeah i mean obviously there's technical
questions because what we're saying here
just to kind of drive the point home
we're saying
we don't think veto should be the only
tool that will let you map these rabbit
holes we want a lot of different tools
to be able to do this and interoperate
with each other that's one thing that's
kind of okay
because it raises a lot of confusing
questions about you know okay how do you
guys monetize this stuff like where are
where you know where is the data getting
stored and how
people not feeling your data or
yeah how are you maybe getting uh
compensated for people using your data
in different kinds of services
um so we're aware that there are a lot
of
challenging questions there like we're
not naive about that but we do think
that these kind of questions are joining
you know broader questions in web three
space of data sovereignty and
decentralized identity and
yeah all the bigger questions that a lot
of people are working on and we see
ourselves sort of interfacing with them
and you know people might in a modular
way like if someone has a good solution
for
you know renumerating people on their
data stations
[Music]
yep bring it to active inference and
maybe go to the second of the active
inference slides
uh first and break it off
awesome
let's get back here
and the next slide
we'll come back to the general questions
but i just wanted to start with this one
um highlight some awesome recent work
and provide like an example based entry
point
to the intersection of attention
which is often used very abstractly or
in a single entity case in active
inference or in a non-stigmatic setting
how attention is being used and bring it
to like a very clear applied case
so this is the recent work of albarasan
at all from this year
and they are
making a model of kind of like a toy
twitter
where individuals are involved in just
like in any active inference model
they're involved in perception cognition
and action and then impact in the niche
and in this case
what is being perceived from the niche
what the generative process is handing
those entities is information that in
this case is being proxied by different
hashtags so you know yes on x no on x
of course hashtags have much more
complex usage simply tagging content or
using or not using one can see many ways
that the hashtag is not the whole
semantic picture but again it serves as
a proxy
and as an expansible platform
to make models that could include
different kinds of communication
and
on the left is a a graphical
representation of how this simulation
plays out and so a simulation like this
can be used prospectively given a set of
parameters to evaluate different futures
it can also be used given empirical data
to tune those parameters and in fact
there can be kind of a bi-directionality
or a tale of two cities tale of two
densities where empirical data are
coming in
and updating parameters and then those
updated parameters are used in a
generative capacity
again to look at counterfactuals or to
simulate futures
and it's called a graphical model
because it's based upon a bayesian
graphical network model
the nodes whether they're a circle or
square
there's some
details to go into but the nodes are
variables so that would be like x equals
those are the nodes
and that would be equivalent to like a
variable in a script
so whether you think about this more
mathematically or more from a
programming an implementation
angle
the nodes are like the variables and the
edges represent relationships amongst
the variables
and for those who have more familiarity
with this type of representation of an
active inference model they'll
see what some of these letters mean and
what roles they might be playing here
but suffice to say that this graphical
network here
is representing
the cognitive context of multiple
entities that are receiving information
in the form of hashtag
doing some cognitive process on it
updating their beliefs as well as
choosing how to act
and then implementing that action and
then that is like one time step in the
simulation so i wanted to provide this
example because it's a great
case study
of bringing active inference into a
social and digital
setting
and it's a great direction that uses
also the pi mdp package
developed by some of the authors and
others so it's a great
case on multiple sides to understand how
research developments
and open source software development
can meet up with socially relevant cases
so wanted to just describe that case
if either of you have any thoughts or
questions and then the next case that
we'll look into will be more of an ant
case
and that will help bring us to some of
these bigger questions about attention
and stigma chi
yeah i was just going to say um
this kind of circles back i think to the
one of the first lines we were talking
about is this kind of stewardship of
global collective behavior
paper which was kind of uh
you know
pulling out the fact that there's no
ethical or scientific oversight over the
large platforms and then saying this is
something like how
you know how how an oversight might look
and actually it's more than over there
right because actually it's even deeper
than oversight because it's actually
like you might imagine
this being involved in sort of
intervention in platforms just being
able to uh if you have recommendation
services this could like inform
uh you know how to update parameters the
recommendation service based on observed
behavior of the network uh so yeah
beyond oversight even sort of like this
kind of collective decentralized control
we were alluding to so i think this is
like a more concrete instance of how
that might look a very fascinating kind
of direction a modeling direction that
people can maybe find interested
and it also really highlights the
relevance of a bottom-up agentic
perspective not just because we then can
talk about pluralism and diversity of
perspectives much more easily but even
the kinds of design
interventions and suggestions are going
to be different if we think about this
from like the top-down
content depositing
or the bottom-up approach like imagine
if we wanted the ants in the colony to
be in a different location
and we're putting all these articles in
one location
we're making so much amazing content
promoting this
idea
but of course if the entities are not
navigating to it and reinforcing that
trail you could spend all the money on
advertising and it would just dissipate
as soon as that like life support for
the trail were gone
and so when we take that bottom up
attention-based perspective it really
puts us like in the view from the inside
from the participant
what are they perceiving which is always
going to be extremely limited
and then what are they updating their
beliefs in terms of and then how are
they choosing to act given the
affordances they have so the bottom-up
perspective brings in all these very
important
discussions around like accessibility in
discourse and
perspective integration
and then treats it as like something
that might be addressed
at the level where it's occurring which
is at the entity or the actor level
rather than being like well there's 500
petabytes of data and this is how much
the system does on this high level
those are abstract metrics again with a
with an economic analogy it'd be like
macroeconomics and then behavioral and
like neuro and micro economics
one can just put piles of product in
different locations but unless there's
individuals who are interested in it and
prefer it and
allocate their attention to it
nothing will occur
maybe another just like to try a
concrete
example for that could be
you know a will brought up this uh
then the dashboard of the fox news
versus cnn so you might imagine like you
know stewards of some futuristic uh
social network or you know social i look
at the kind of attention data we're
talking about collecting here and they
might be able to through these kind of
modeling approaches because okay you
know we what if we want to optimize this
network uh
for you know
rent coverage and like get people to see
diverse viewpoints and stuff like that
like how are the which recommendation
services we use and how should we tune
them
uh yeah and then sort of seeing the
effect of that and be able to learn how
to collectively steward
attention and you know again this open
source people can participate in it
yeah in directions that are more healthy
for society
one last thought before going to the
next slide is um
in the vo traces
we saw about how what was being
presented or provided or curated wasn't
necessarily the granular content so not
the newsletter that says here's the five
things you want to look at or hear
ranked by whatever metric novelty or by
importance or popularity
here are the granular atomic pieces of
content for you to look at
when we can
curate
and in in a consensual way
determine
how transitions amongst content
are coming into play that's like the
true value okay so you're on the
wikipedia page for active inference or
you're on the wikipedia page for some
historical entity
maybe that content is just so amazing it
stands alone but the reality is it's
part of our epistemic forging our
learning journeys and so being able to
connect dots is quite literally
understanding okay for somebody who is
in a given context and language
experience
this intro to python should link to this
next resource but then of course there's
many links so there's no reason to
collapse that pathway
to like a hallway
it kind of respects the actual dynamics
of the information environment
in a few interesting ways um let's go to
the next slide because it it connects
some more points yeah
the back ones are backwards or uh
the forwards
okay so um in 2021
with some colleagues i worked on a ant
colony simulation where the individual
nest mates were utilizing an active
inference model of perception cognition
action
and those actions were spatial movement
in a tea maze so in a foraging space
and then one other action that they had
the opportunity to do upon finding food
was to deposit pheromone so no pheromone
was being deposited until the food was
detected and then upon kind of turning
around a pheromone deposition occurred
and it was decaying in the environment
now
it's a kind of fun link
to look at the
place where that
core
model of epistemic foraging
being foraging in a space
and looking for something seeking for
something having a preference to find
something
that we used in the ant
spatial foraging case
for finding the food resource in the
teammates
it was adapted from
a
earlier slash different paper
by axel constant at all
and the paper was acquisition of
culturally patterned attention styles
under active inference
and so the setting is very
creative and subtle which is that
there's a tic-tac-toe grid so a three by
three grid
that is representing like the visual
scope
of someone who's looking at something so
they're
s
um staring or they're foveating on the
central point and then they have like a
limited range of peripheral vision and
then outside of that there's much less
visual acuity
they were involved in an epistemic
foraging task so
unlike where in reward learning the
decisions of where to move and how to
move might be dictated by what is
perceived as the most pragmatically
rewarding state or paths towards
pragmatic reward
in this information foraging case
which has been also um explored a lot of
other eye movements active inference
simulations
it's driven by epistemic foraging
reducing uncertainty about what kind of
pattern one is existing in
and so it's almost like reading braille
except it's with our eyes because we of
course don't
see at the same resolution the whole
page
at the same time in fact the clarity
outside of your main visual region and
the clarity even in your blind spot is
part of our generative model of vision
but putting that aside what the entities
are doing in this
pottery scanning task
is actually scanning locally and using
the local patterns that they're seeing
with a relationship of like okay is it
like a line going across or line going
up or is there a diagonal
understanding the motifs that they're
perceiving
to reduce their uncertainty about what
kind of pottery they're looking at
and this
the only tweak
main tweak that we had to make
to bring it into a spatial foraging
context was thinking okay instead of the
point
at the center of the visual gaze
instead of that just being like the x y
coordinate of where one is looking at
we're going to make that the body
position of the nest mate
and so visual foraging you can scan and
you can you can like teleport or move
very rapidly
but it doesn't leave a trace
you could look over something many times
and it's not going to modify the object
in the ink case because it's this
embodied spatial foraging
they are
only able to move locally
and they do under all slash sum
situations
physically modify the niche and i think
it really closes the loop with what
ronin brought up earlier with like eye
gaze
and other brain computer interfaces are
taking
invisible
stigmergic markers
of attention
and making them into visible markers
like heat gaze
analysis or heat maps of gaze not sure
what they call it it is often used like
in advertising
um where people might present two
versions of a page or a product and see
where people are looking in terms of the
label and other features
do we have or use that kind of approach
for education
do we proactively use it do people field
test different layouts of papers
so that's an interesting thought and um
oh yeah
i just want to
yeah i definitely feel like uh the whole
i was thinking just like um
yeah i feel like a whole new sort of
yeah field of epistemic engineering for
like there's so many
both like them you know fury engineering
yeah practice they're all at all
different levels there's just like
yeah it's like
pretty wide blue motion space
for different kind of techniques
modeling this is really cool i like how
you bridge
between sites like the site where we
have here like the affiliation and the
ant movement like it's really
interesting like how and each hand is
sort of like a sensor of the collective
organism
so
yeah it almost felt like what we're
trying to build and for social networks
kind of like
we're trying to build like a seismograph
or something like that like uh
epidemic seismograph
[Music]
yeah by using making this kind of what
you're saying the individuals
or another kind of visual mixed metaphor
if there's a top-down
attention determiner
it's like the eye of mordor in lord of
the rings it's like a laser that's like
leaving like a a
a scar
where it's scanning so it could be
modifying the environment or not but
it's like one strong laser
versus like seeing as like many
distributed eyes
that are in local feedback loops so
their
cognitive burden if we think about the
actual biology of it or their
computational burden
if we think about simulating this system
would be lower and more paralyzable
and wouldn't require any entity to have
access to information that we know it
can't have like how do people interact
with markets well they don't have the
time series data from the last 10 years
loaded into memory but the analyst might
but the individual is actually on this
journey seeing random things from
different times and so if we wanted to
understand decision making in that
setting we would want to be taking or at
least complementing the top down with a
bottom-up view and so it's the case in
economics
and it's also the case in our epistemic
environments
though those are um
[Music]
corralled in a way that keeps the
discourse
on certain
areas
yeah i
well we kind of talked about a little
before i feel like this there's another
whole wrap hole to talk about how
this kind of uh
how much you want to bring in this sort
of machine aided decision making because
we understand that like humans like on
one side i really i can see where you're
going with like the sort of how local
agents are making sense of local
environments that's sort of creating
this global more global trends making uh
but then i know we also know that humans
like when
when we choose for example you know what
path from this like social view we're
eventually we're going to use ai to sort
of integrate histories of people that
have traversed those paths besides you
know here suggest like a few to go on so
i think that's just the delicate uh
balance between
maintaining human agency and
[Music]
interpretability that like know what
they're doing they're not just like
following blind visa instructions from
algorithms
versus really needing algorithms to make
sense to crunch the data
but doing it in a way it doesn't sort of
uh
i think that i've heard it's called like
yeah algorithms that disintermediate
humans i think it's kind of like the
human is like a peripheral part of the
sense the sense making good
yeah there's definitely like a delicate
block to
walk there
uh
yeah
let's go
let's go to the first um active
inference slide and then so we have kind
of two slides of general questions to
raise
some of them
to to
bring us out from those more specific
examples
some general active inference questions
and then we can um
close with the open challenges
so just the first one was what is
attention in active inference and how is
it being used because there's a
technical usage of attention that's
common in bayesian statistics like you
could hear about a neural network with
an attention module or even a simpler
kind of model with attention as a
parameter and it relates to how much new
observations are updating your priors so
if you have no attention on an
observation it's not updating your
priors
so that is equivalent to not paying
attention it's like there's things
you're not seeing behind you you're not
paying any attention they're not being
used up to your priors whereas if you're
super paying attention to something
then you're going to be updating your
priors to its location or what it's um
telling you so where have we seen that
kind of motif
in active inference
and how did it play a role in the
alberosen at all paper and how does it
play a role in these kinds of
simulations
second questions like a very
general question that we ask all the
time which is just where and how is
active inference being applied are those
conceptual or schematic simulations or
are these real-time data processing
systems which almost inevitably are
going to require
technical solutions that aren't like
just
the active inference entity loop that's
kind of like the kernel
but then there's a technological system
that uses the kernel just like the
linear model kernel like y equals mx
plus b
that is so simple can be written down
yet in practice there needs to be a lot
of architecture and multilinear
aggressions and so on so this is a
different kernel for modeling this kind
of an active situation
and also the systems need to have more
than just an insightful kernel
to be of any utility let alone function
um
the third point we recently had a
symposium on active inference and
robotics where we had about uh nine
presenters who share different work
that is involving
the realization of robotic systems
implementing active inference and
to see the kinds of uh topics that they
were bringing to the front like
affective robotics robots that are
dealing with us as affective entities
but also robots that even have
computational
emulations of affect like what if a
robot could have a frustration parameter
but it used that to not go down a road
that it wasn't really finding value in
for example or boredom if the
information wasn't good or excitement if
it were good so those kinds of affects
have a technical and computational usage
in active inference models
and then i think the the last question
that brings us to
the more open questions and a lot of the
other threads that our co-authors have
been bringing in
is like where is design in this and
humor human-centered
design
graphical design and the user interface
but
taking that as like the tip of the
iceberg
and how do we bring in
proactive
thinking around what kinds of systems
and experiences that are to be curated
how does that design thinking
[Music]
meld with cognitive science
in a positive way
cool yeah i
one thing you mentioned i think this was
in the beginning when we started working
on this research
you asked this question it kind of stuck
with me you said something about like
yeah we have
like what are we doing with all the
cognitive science theories if we're not
using them like
like you're saying that effect it's like
yeah they're not
we're not
implementing the theories in practice
like often when they're building
products
so
it seems yeah this seems like a really
interesting kind of theory
integrating with practice to build yeah
information landscapes uh yeah very very
i think cognizant has a lot to say
here
i'm excited to see how this gets kind of
integrated
i like how it kind of gets gets a little
uh meta too so
you have
i i like what you said earlier you said
epistemic engineering i would
i'm i'm kind of inclined to reframe it
as like epistemic design epistemic
environment design in which
agents are using their understanding of
active inference to develop systems
that allow individuals to
interact with the world in a way that's
used as active inference so it's sort of
like and i mean that's kind of what um
i believe that i've heard it phrased as
active open-mindedness that's a sort of
like self reflection it's this this
ability to evaluate your own cognitive
processes update your models and your
own cognitive processes in ways that
allow you to interact with other
external information so that you can
continue to update your models where
they might otherwise become entrenched
in overconfidence and confirmation bias
and whatnot and this is kind of taking
it out of that individualistic paradigm
and applying it in a collective paradigm
where you're you're by designing uh
ecosystems epistemic ecosystems that
allow people to best leverage those
innate qualities without even thinking
about it
um we're kind of
reaping the same benefit
to some extent that people would gain
from like deep um somewhat critical or
at least
um
humble and skeptical introspection
which is active inference applied to
itself in a sense
yeah i yeah maybe maybe
it is pretty meta which i think is
really cool and i just maybe maybe
uh try to connect it to some things
people might be familiar with i think
tristan harris often speaks about like
the sort of current technology which is
sort of race to the bottom that it keeps
like if it it sort of thrives on
exploiting
our different vulnerabilities cognitive
vulnerabilities um
and profiting off those but at this sort
of the externality is that you know
we're degrading human cognition
here this really i feel like we're in
this sort of trying to be in the space
of
race to the top which is another
kind of thing that tristan harris i've
heard him
yeah trying to think about technology
the way that yeah it's actually making
us more open-minded more attuned to sort
of our space and the collective like
where we're repeating like collective
stance making and yeah i feel like it's
really racing how do we get people
how do we build technology to make
people more yeah critically reflective
and open-minded all those things
and we have to apply those principles to
do it we have to understand those things
we have to know what
means help bring it about yeah that's
build technology open-mindedness
the meta
maybe a last active comment which will
go to our last slide is like will what
you mentioned with uh active
open-mindedness which is surely a term
that preceded active inference
but
it it force ages
that
active engagement
and then the dilemma or tension or
dialectic between like what we bring to
the table
and then what the table
is providing to us and so if it were um
some other kind of product design we're
making a soft drink
are we gonna barge in with assumptions
and then what are the danger modes of
that but also what is the danger of just
what every single person tells you
putting too much attention
on the specifics overfitting to those 20
people and making some kind of like
chimera that only appeals to them and
that would be one thing
in the food engineering and food design
case
but this is the leverage point
on digital communication
and so it becomes even more
of
immediacy
because this is like the coefficient on
how we communicate and share and learn
nowadays
and also like puts in these higher order
questions like we were talking about
earlier which is there's always going to
be an argument for centralization and
that's not to say that one extreme is
better than other it's always contextual
but there always is an argument to just
do it faster internally
rather than potentially avert
a deeper
failure mode
but there are other challenges arising
with decentralized systems so
there's no
generalized free lunch
but then the question could be like but
could there be information environments
and regimes of action and regimes of
attention
that are consensual and also productive
and so on so i agree it's been an
awesome um
and and to bring in will with yours and
lauren's
experience on design
and seeing design
as like
almost
the art and science and practice of
bringing the counter factual and the
adjacent possible
via
inference into
something that
is implemented so i i think there's a
lot to connect there
so maybe let's go to our last um slide
and then if anybody in the live chat has
any thoughts or questions
otherwise um ronan looking forward to
hearing these
yeah just stamps yeah episodic design
you feel like there's the whole like
full stack episodes like there's design
engineering all the
and in between um but yeah so we were
talking about you know some of the sort
of trade-offs between the things
yeah where we are now and you know
centralized systems and decentralized
systems
there are a lot of open challenges here
uh some of them we kind of already
talked about so i'll go through them but
uh
yeah and just kind of finish on some of
these things that we're looking at i was
trying to make progress with our
research proposal and development and
all that
um
so yeah i think
you know one thing is definitely that
we're
in sort of what can we do right now to
help uh clean up our information systems
given that you know many of these tools
don't exist yet and they're sort of
i guess a lot of people would say these
are like
it could be a decade-long project to
build these kind of interoperable
protocols um
so yeah where what do we do right now i
think yeah if anyone has thoughts on
that
if we're going to raise those otherwise
you can just i'll run through them all
if you have thoughts you can go back to
it um
yeah i think there's this kind of
you know we talked about
a few times during the conversation you
have this kind of user which is the
local minima of convenience so users are
just like they're getting used and
they're using software but but it's
really like this kind of very convenient
local minima and get stuck in it how do
you transition towards more active
sensitive role uh there's a lot of sort
of culture and norms and
social aspects here that we can
definitely also
dive deeper into but yeah
probably have future conversations with
that um
and yeah there's no the protocol problem
which we're uh mindful of where this is
i think best express but it's xkcd comic
you know you have some kind of
uh situation where you want to introduce
the new standard but they're
then you already standard
try to generalize everyone else's
protocols and now they're like shifting
protocols and you're stuck in the same
situation
um
yeah this is a problem i don't know any
of you like really great results i mean
i'm not aware of so many success stories
here so it is clear we have like
a challenge uh facing us but um
on the other hand web 3 seems to be all
about tackling this protocol so we feel
like we're
yeah in good company at least
thinking about this
yeah
will you want to add something or
uh yeah one of the things i love the
um
second one um and i think one of the
things that
resonates with me is i think it speaks
to one of the original explicit goals of
vo which is
like obviously this is a huge problem
and one of the things we were trying to
do in designing that interface is to
make it as convenient as possible to be
an active sensemaker
and
largely this is driven by by my own
research process i have
adhd i have a very hard time getting
through uh research paper so i was
actually
like we were trying to find a way to
make
going through this process that seems
really overwhelming to some people
including myself
um a lot more convenient but a lot more
simple and taking a lot of that like the
labor burden off so that um like the
person's mind is free to think and
record and doesn't have to actually
manage like really what is a fairly
sophisticated process
for people who i mean both of you are
you know
seasoned academics you you know that
it's not a trivial skill to be able to
to go through loads of information and
extract what's meaningful and figure out
where you need to delve into new um
arenas and
if you can make
that process that requires a lot of
discipline and planning and structures
and
um whatnot if you can make that very
convenient then all of a sudden you can
just think about the thing think about
the information and the ideas that are
in the information so
um
of course
we don't have that tool yet so what can
we do right now
nice thanks will just a few other um
comments the interoperability
we brought up earlier um the content is
often highly interoperable today
like whether you can download it
directly or right click save or use obs
to screencap pretty much any content can
be delivered on another platform you can
share text or an image you found on one
location to another so in many ways
amidst the platforms jumping from
platform to platform we have
interoperable content because we have
like file types for content jpeg
um
and
running you highlighted the
interoperability
of these attention markers the ones that
we have today the the likes and so on
but then the ones that we could have
tomorrow with all these other kinds of
interfaces
and then i um wondered well where are we
at with financial interoperability
is there
a way for even this one special kind of
data
like a ledger
or some kind of bookkeeping
what are the interoperability mechanisms
that exist for financial data and then
would the knowledge case
be easier or harder
and then what happened this um 14 and
then going to 15
so how does the financial
information stay coherent with markets
there isn't an interoperability layer
necessarily directly
between
two currencies
but then there are different kinds of
intermediators
who can be clear or obscure
with why they're providing some kind of
exchange and so i think that points to
like information exchanges
before some kind of sweeping
knowledge generalization synthesis
like a future knowledge protocol
there would be many options
for just like the apis
and the kind of web scraping and
re-parsing techniques exist today to to
act as markets
that help swap
different information
um and then one other point to make was
we
talked also about like what is opaque
and what is transparent
and in some earlier
uh
active streams actually on like
consciousness and attention and
awareness we had an interesting
discussion around transparency and
opaque
a transparent
thing is something that you can't see
you see through it because you can't see
it
something that's opaque
you do see
because you can't see through it
so what aspects of the system
should be transparent
which isn't to say
we could investigate the source code
because that would actually be opacity
and one could say well it's fully
documented totally comprehensive opacity
well that's great
but what are the parts of the system
that are transparent like the water we
swim in
that would be
not visible
and then what are the parts of the
system where people would see them and
know them
and those would be opaque
yeah that's been awesome but like that's
a
kind of mind-blowing thought um i
yeah that kind of brings to mind you
know little distinction
on
making like convenience isn't always i
was treating it here as sort of
something that's kind of cursed but he
was saying it can also be
a
doom or benefit uh the right thing is
made convenient and it kind of seems
like what you're saying also is
we need to make the right things like
just like you know the interface like a
cell phone you know the right things
that are opaque and the right things are
transparent where the importance is for
controlling it the relevant affordances
for controlling it are the ones that you
see
the ones you don't need to see you don't
see so
yeah probably something like that it
seems like like again
design how to make uh information
landscapes that sort of show you the
right levers and
obscure the things you don't need to see
so you can not get overwhelmed
and probably being able to end this kind
of openness you know the open source
quality of them means that different
people will want different levels so
some people really want to play with the
nuts and bolts and other people just
want to like have like simple interfaces
but allowing all that span of
uh
of interfaces i think is part of the
yeah yeah it's just not like this kind
of plurality aspect you were talking
about i think it's really important that
different people will see different
interfaces based on liquids what's best
for them
that's one of the biggest advantages of
having this interoperability is now we
have an opportunity to take what is
ultimately the same data set and
make
interfaces make
end user applications
that are tailored to particular needs or
people or use cases or accessibility um
needs and whatnot
so that
really niche groups of people can
interact on this broad scale in a way
that specifically suits them that can't
be accommodated with a platform or with
like kind of a one-size-fits-all
approach to um
manipulating with engaging with
interacting with this data this
information information
yeah one quick comment on the
accessibility because i think it it
really
distinguishes
the uh semi tectonic the building like
stigma g from the attention like stigma
g so
content accessibility
is the prerequisite
for there to be
the trail
content accessibility could include like
screen reader affordances changing the
font size changing the colors um making
sure that just like the open science
movement has been highlighting like that
the content quite literally is
accessible in any form let alone one
that accounts for like sensory
differences but just making the content
available
has to be a first step
and then
what does
attention accessibility look like
so like if previously it was like we
need that pdf
accessible
not behind a paywall okay
content accessibility with preprint
servers
to a large extent in the scientific
domain just speaking narrowly like that
content is accessible
and then what are all the trails
that go from this one pre-print
website and pdf
and the way that these 700 people had
these thoughts and these 300 people had
these thoughts
that's
that transition amongst different
content
and giving visibility
to that content
because that content is being recorded
and it is being used to shape attention
but through this covert
platform-owned loop
rather than
us being able to like be like
i want to publicly add this comment on
the paper
and then this is just i want this to be
only in my private information or
something like that um but i think that
really like highlights that
accessibility isn't just the font size
genre
there's another
connecting the dots kind of
accessibility
that doesn't exist
even like on the radar
because it feels like well what do you
need to understand the scientific paper
beyond having access to the pdf it's
like you need like everything
and now that can be a a clearer
conversation
yeah yeah i love that acceptability is
broader than just the content
acceptability to the reactions
of people the content
yeah
well any other like thoughts or
directions or information you want to
share feel free to go for it
yeah this was great i mean just
really it's fun to dive into all these
things
uh
yeah so many quick questions and i just
again reiterated you know it'll take a
lot of minds to think about these things
and work on these things a lot of
different types of minds builders and
all that so yeah if you're interested by
any of this then we're really welcoming
collaborators
awesome yeah we can have like a 26.2
we can always continue the series and
and
um like version and update and include
others in the conversation so great
presentation and thanks both for joining
thank you
for putting this on
yeah thanks so much
goodbye
see ya
okay
it's done
it is fun
yeah um
there's a few there's a few things one
is to just
share it and ask people but it is um
it's an hour and a half long